Every programming language has a means by which
dates and times can be formatted in several
ways. Python is no exception. Some apps use fixed
dates, while others need to know the current date,
such as when a game logs a current date and time
as a starting point for a game based on timing.
The current date and time are located within the
datetime library, which needs to be imported.
I’ve done just that on line 1 of this 622-datetime
file. On line 2, we have a current time variable;
in just a moment, we will replace the comment
with the current date and time. Line 3 has a
print statement with a message that includes the
current time variable. Let’s return to line 2 and
determine what we need to get the current date
and time to show. I will use the tips I get when
typing code in the Visual Studio Code editor.
I will select and delete the comment. Then,
I will type the library name, datetime, and a
dot. We see a list of possibilities for where
to go next. As we want the current date and time,
I will choose datetime. Then, I will type another
dot. In many programming languages, the current
date and time keyword is either current_time or
now. In scrolling through this list, we see now. I
will select it and then add a set of parentheses,
as all built-in methods need them. I will
run the code, and the date and time show,
but I think you would agree that the formatting
could use some help. The strftime method allows
one to format a date and time to a presentable
format. For example, let’s say we want to format
this date in mm/dd/yyyy hh:mm format. First, we
need to add the strftime method to the current
time and then add parentheses to put the argument
in for the format we want. I will place the cursor
in parentheses, and the general principle with
strftime is that each format piece starts with a
percent symbol and then has a letter to designate
the desired format. I will type %m-%d-%y and add
quotes around this text. To try this out and then
run this code. That is very close to what we want.